Finding Aid for Henry Earle Riggs papers, 1911-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Earle Riggs papers 1911-1942
Riggs, Henry Earle, b. 1865
2 linear feet
852137 Aa 2
Professor of civil engineering at University of Michigan. Railroad valuation and appraisal files; lectures and reports; personal materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Finley B. Riggs (donor no. 3108 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born on May 8, 1853 in Lawrence, Kansas, Henry E. Riggs graduated in 1886 from the University of Kansas with the degree of A.B., after a five-year literary and engineering course. In 1910 he received the degree of C.E. from the University of Michigan. On graduation from the University of Kansas he entered railway service as a axman on the B. & M. Railroad in Nebraska. In the fall of 1887 he entered the service of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railroad. From March 1, 1890, to January 1, 1896, he was Chief Engineer of the Ann Arbor Railroad. From 1896 to 1912 he was a member of the Riggs and Sherman Company of Toledo, Ohio, engaged in design and construction of sewerage, water works, paving, electric railway and industrial railroads.
In 1900 he was one of the two principal assistants of Mortimer E. Cooley on the Michigan appraisal of railroad properties. His career since then was largely devoted to problems of valuation and depreciation of railroads. He was consulting engineer on valuation matters for the states of Michigan, New York, and Georgia; for a number of municipalities; and for railroads, including the New York Central System, the Illinois Central System, the Norfolk and Western, the Virginian, the Union Pacific, the St. Louis-San Francisco, and the Pere Marquette.
From 1912 to 1930 Riggs was professor and head of the department of civil engineering of the University of Michigan. On June 30, 1930, he retired with the title of Honorary Professor of Civil Engineering.
Riggs died July 5, 1949.
The Henry Earle Riggs collection includes correspondence and documents, 1914-1924, relating to valuation of the Detroit United Railway. This includes correspondence removed from the files of Mortimer E. Cooley. There are also other materials relating to public utilities valuation, civil engineering, and public works, mainly lectures, addresses, articles, and testimony.
Of special note is a file of correspondence relating to University of Michigan Civil Engineering alumni killed in World War I, file on the history of the Ann Arbor Railroad, and a 1942 speech describing problems of the proposed Willow Run, Michigan, wartime housing development.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Railroad Company.; Detroit United Railway.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Public utilities--Michigan.; Railroads--Michigan.; Street-railroads--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; Willow Run (Mich.); World War, 1914-1918.; Riggs, Henry Earle, b. 1865.
Contributors:
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Hemans, Lawton T. (Lawton Thomas), 1864-1916.; Smith, William Morris, b. 1870.
Genre Terms:
genre
- Railroad valuation and appraisal files
  - Ann Arbor Railroad testimony, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Detroit United Railway
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Mortimer E. Cooley files
      - 1914 (Box 1)
      - 1915-1916 (Box 1)
      - 1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920 (Box 1)
    - Henry E. Riggs files
      - 1922 (Box 1)
      - 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - Documents (primarily typescript copies)
      - 1915 (Box 1)
      - 1919 (Box 1)
      - 1921 (Box 1)
      - 1922
        - Payroll, 3 folders (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - 1923
        - Public Utilities Commission testimony, February 6-14, 1923, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Riggs report to Detroit United Railway (DUR), September 24, 1923 (Box 1)
        - Riggs statement to Public Utilities Commission (PUC), May 1923 ? (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - 1924 (Box 1)
- Lectures and reports
  - 1911 and 1915 and 1924 testimony (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936 (Box 1)
    (include letter from John E. Hodge reminiscing about class activities, ca. 1888)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1942 re Willow Run housing (Box 1)
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - "Lectures and reports, university matters and transportation, with two early reports on depreciation", 1 volume (Box 2)
  - "Lectures, memoranda, testimony", 1 volume (Box 2)
  - "Miscellaneous papers and reports, valuation, depreciation, and accounting", 1 volume (Box 2)
  - "Thirty years development in public utility valuation", 1 volume (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous and personal
  - University of Michigan Civil Engineering alumni who died in World War I, correspondence 1924-1926 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and related materials assembled by sons Finley B. and Samuel for planned biography of HER (Box 2)